<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A memorial of the kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ near approaching declaring according to prophecy, and advising upon the state of princes and nations, and of these nations in particular, what our Israel ought to do, in order to it, most humbly, and yet with the authority of sacred prophecy, presented to the King, and to the Queen, and to the high court of Parliament, and to all the judges of the nation / by T. Beverley ...</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16218789</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16218789</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27617)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1087:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A memorial of the kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ near approaching declaring according to prophecy, and advising upon the state of princes and nations, and of these nations in particular, what our Israel ought to do, in order to it, most humbly, and yet with the authority of sacred prophecy, presented to the King, and to the Queen, and to the high court of Parliament, and to all the judges of the nation / by T. Beverley ...</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Prophecies.</term>
               <term>Prophecy --  Christianity.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A MEMORIAL OF THE KINGDOM OF OUR <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> NEAR APPROACHING; Declaring according to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and Adviſing upon the State of Princes and Nations, and of theſe Nations in particular, what our <hi>Iſrael ought to do,</hi> in Order to it; Moſt Humbly, and yet with the Authority of <hi>Sacred Prophecy,</hi> Preſented to the <hi>KING,</hi> and to the <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN,</hi> and to the <hi>High Court of Parliament,</hi> and to All the <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By <hi>T. Beverley,</hi> a moſt Humble <hi>Reader</hi> in the <hi>Propheſies</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>IN the firſt place, I look upon it as my duty, to Produce my Credentials before ſo Awful an Authority, to whom all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Reverence, and Humbleſt Obeiſances according to the <hi>Ordinance of Christ,</hi> are from Me moſt due; Even as from Them unto the <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> The <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Credentials</hi> I Lay before this <hi>Auguſt Preſence</hi> is;<note place="margin">Revel. 19.10.</note> 
               <hi>The Teſtimony of Jeſus</hi> concerning <hi>Things yet</hi> to <hi>Come</hi> to <hi>Paſs,</hi> however Receiv'd, is the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Angel,</hi> whoſe words theſe are, was the Primier Miniſter of <hi>Prophecy</hi> from Chriſt, to the <hi>Apocalyptical Apoſtle John; John</hi> would therefore have <hi>Worſhipp'd</hi> Him; He Refus'd it upon this Account, beſide other Great ones; The <hi>Teſtimony of Chriſt in Prophecy,</hi> Receiv'd by <hi>John,</hi> gave <hi>John</hi> an equal Character in the main with Himſelf, the <hi>Angel:</hi> Becauſe the Principal Character in <hi>Prophecy</hi> is the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus</hi> in any Point of <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105103:2"/>
            <p>Even ſo, whoſoever are Guided by God into the True Senſe of <hi>Scripture Prophecy</hi> are therefore, and ſo far as They have indeed the <hi>Mind of Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> Equal, even with the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and with the <hi>Angel</hi> in the Spirit of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> Seeing the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> and not the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> is the Spirit of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> that is, not only of the Supreme, but of the Alone Authority; and All the <hi>Miniſters</hi> in that <hi>Teſtimony</hi> are <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Fellow Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that God hath been pleas'd of his own <hi>Free Grace</hi> and <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and becauſe ſo hath it <hi>Seemed Good in his Sight</hi> to vouchſafe to me, I Humbly, and Heartily Acknowledge to the <hi>Shame,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of my Face</hi> (before ſo Awful Supreme Powers on Earth), the <hi>Chiefeſt of Sinners;</hi> He hath been pleas'd on the moſt Earneſt, and Conſtant Attendances upon the <hi>Propheſies</hi> of his <hi>Word</hi> for theſe <hi>Seven Years</hi> laſt paſt, by Meditation and Prayer, and by Compare of the Grander, and moſt Indubitable <hi>Revolutions</hi> of the World, to vouchſafe to me a Clear and Conſiſtent <hi>Table of Prophetical Scripture,</hi> in <hi>Analogy</hi> to all <hi>Scripture,</hi> and to which Thoſe <hi>Revolutions</hi> have Anſwer'd, even as <hi>Face Anſwers to Face in a Glaſs;</hi> So that Having ſuch a perfect Scheme in Agreement with Event, I muſt needs have the ſame Aſſurance that I Have of the <hi>Analogy of Faith,</hi> ſo Admirably Conſenting with all True <hi>Reaſon;</hi> Or that <hi>Anatomists</hi> have of the <hi>Compage</hi> of <hi>Humane Bodies,</hi> or <hi>Aſtronomers of the Heavens,</hi> Although I eaſily Acknowledge there is much more to be known, then I have Attain'd, or can Attain, although I preſs forward yet with all my Might.</p>
            <p>I have therefore made ſeveral Appeals in publick to All the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Scripture,</hi> in <hi>Chronology,</hi> in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> to ſhew the Inconſiſtences of the <hi>Scheme</hi> in Any part, and have not yet Found Any, either ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for ſome Injur'd Truth in any of Thoſe Diſcourſes, (beſides the Charity due from Chriſtians to Any one in Error) or for their own particular Sentiments, that would undertake to convince it of Abſurdity; Although in the late <hi>Reign,</hi> One particular Printed Writing, Grounded on that <hi>Scheme,</hi> Immediately directed againſt the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> Entitled, <hi>The Call of God out of Babylon</hi> was of ſo Publick a notice, as that ſome Books were ſeiz'd from my own Hand by the then Officers of the Preſs, and as they ſaid, to be carried to the <hi>Councel;</hi> And although I have preſented ſome Parts of Them to the <hi>Biſhops:</hi> Particularly, One call'd <hi>The Reformation to be Reform'd.</hi> And I ſtill Place my ſelf at the ſame Judgment Seat.</p>
            <p>My Second <hi>Credential</hi> is, That of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> When the <hi>Word of the Prophet is Come to paſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerem. 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>Then ſhall it be known,</hi> that the <hi>Lord hath ſent Him.</hi> I therefore Appeal to Three Great Events, wherein <hi>Providence</hi> hath <hi>Set to its Seal,</hi> that I have Truly Judged according to Grounds of <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That I have Freely, and as Publickly as I could, declar'd, that when All Things ſeem'd to be moving towards it, It would be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105103:2"/> wholly Impoſſible to Re-Inſlave theſe Nations, which were by the <hi>Reformation,</hi> ſuch an Eminent Appearance of Chriſt from <hi>Heaven,</hi> Reſcued from the <hi>Papal Tyranny;</hi> And I thought it my Duty to pray as publickly as I had opportunity, for the <hi>Converſion</hi> of that our then <hi>Prince,</hi> as being Aſſur'd, He muſt elſe by Death, or ſome mighty Hand (as it Fell out) be Removed from the Government within a ſhort Time; His Adminiſtration being Intollerable to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> in the meaſures which He was ſo Reſolv'd to take; And in the very Spring before his <hi>Removal,</hi> the <hi>Epiſtle to the Reader</hi> in that Forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd diſcourſe, the <hi>Call out of Babylon,</hi> I thus concluded; And as for All <hi>Ambidexters</hi> Two Handed <hi>Achilophelians</hi> or <hi>Judaſſes,</hi> who think to find it in their Account to be on both ſides; as They are now the private Scorn and Deſpiſal of the Age, ſo in Future Records, and not long hence, They will ſtand as <hi>Pillars of Salt;</hi> which how ſoon after, it came to paſs in ſome very Remarkable Perſons, we All know, and who in modeſty to ſome Dead, and ſome Living, are not to be nam'd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Second Event is, What the Nation hath made Publick Acknowledgment of in a Sollemn Thanksgiving. This Summers <hi>Expedition</hi> into <hi>Ireland</hi> of a <hi>Sovereign,</hi> Eſtabliſhed not only by <hi>Civil San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> but by <hi>Prophecy</hi> on the <hi>Throne</hi> of the Former <hi>Prince</hi> Remov'd.</p>
            <p>Now as to this Expedition by a Memorial preſented juſt before it, and I Hope ſtill in many Honourable Hands of Thoſe, to whom I moſt Humbly preſent this, It was according to <hi>Prophecy</hi> predicted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>King's Perſonal Preſence</hi> with his Army in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould be for his Honour: And in Anſwer to this, It may very well be call'd into doubt, whether ever any Prince or General Acquired Greater Glory, according to the Laws of <hi>Warlike Glory</hi> upon his own <hi>Perſonal Fortitude:</hi> But <hi>Prophecy</hi> teaches us to Aſcribe that Glory whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God, as the <hi>Supreme Man of War,</hi> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtyles Him) in that Action; and to Reſerve only the Reflexion, which is indeed Greateſt Honour, to the King, whom God <hi>Commanded not to Fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It was predicted, That God would make it Appear, He had <hi>Commanded Him,</hi> and would by no means <hi>Forſake Him,</hi> but would be <hi>with Him,</hi> as in his <hi>Coming into England,</hi> and would Return Him with Victory.</p>
            <p>And thus it hath come to paſs, The King is Return'd with the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <hi>Thanksgiving of the Nation to God,</hi> and univerſal <hi>Acclamations</hi> to Himſelf; And if any are otherwiſe minded, They are, as in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, <hi>Silent in Darkneſs;</hi> For God hath been pleaſed to paſs the King ſafe, as through a thick Wood of Deaths, to <hi>Cover His Head</hi> as by Miracle in the <hi>Day of Battle;</hi> So to Poize the Motion of that <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Death,</hi> That it came ſo near, as it were to Tell Him,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105103:3"/> and All that Heard of it; It could <hi>Go ſo far,</hi> and <hi>no farther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to the Succeſs of the Expedition, It is ſuch, as that the <hi>Principal City,</hi> and therewith the <hi>Supreme Civil Power</hi> was immediately, and ſo continues <hi>de Facto</hi> veſted in the King. And as a Seal of it; the Former Prince God Remov'd from that <hi>Nation,</hi> even as from this, to declare Him the <hi>Second Time, Intolerable</hi> to <hi>Prophecy;</hi> And as to the delay of a perfect Conqueſt over the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> though <hi>Ireland</hi> be in a daily Motion of <hi>Self Reſtitution</hi> under the Freeſt and Fulleſt <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Government</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation,</hi> Yet It is to be conſidered as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der another <hi>Poſition of Prophecy,</hi> then <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> (the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives having been ſo devoted always to the <hi>Papacy</hi>) until nearer the Great Revolution, the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in Succeſſion at 97. that it will be in a leſs entire Settlement.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was Affirm'd according to <hi>Prophecy;</hi> That God would Secure the King's Intereſts in this Nation during his Abſence; And How even to Amazement was this done in the moſt Peaceable, and even moſt Serene Adminiſtration of the <hi>Supreme Government</hi> by the Queen! and in ſending that Enemy upon the Coaſts back again, even after ſome Succeſs, and Inſolencies of Appearance, without effect in the main! and notwithſtanding a deſign lay'd ſo ſure, that it was thought Impoſſible by the Deſigners, (as ſome expreſs'd Themſelves,) without Miracle, The <hi>Government</hi> ſhould not Revolve on King <hi>James.</hi> And in all this I have often declar'd, God working for <hi>His own Names ſake,</hi> that is, for the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>ſake,</hi> would paſs over the mighty <hi>Provocatians of the Nation,</hi> as is well known to us, He hath done, in all, He hath <hi>done for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A Third Great Event, which gives me Aſſurance; God hath vouchſafed me a True Judgment in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> is; That in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Summer in 87. When the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Affairs gave ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Ruin of that <hi>Empire;</hi> and as I expreſs'd it, the <hi>Turkiſh Fall ſeem'd to be on the Wing,</hi> yet I did with all Freedom, and yet with due Modeſty in Honour to the <hi>Chriſtian Name,</hi> Declare, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, as is yet to be ſeen; That That Ruin or Fall could not be, till the <hi>Tenth,</hi> or <hi>Ten King'd Supremacy</hi> of the <hi>Great City</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould fall; that the <hi>Turkiſh Woe</hi> might paſs away ſo, as that the <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Apoſtaſie,</hi> on which it was, and is a Judgment, might be firſt ſo Animadverted upon by God, that the <hi>Sinful demeritorious Cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>Judicial Effect</hi> might paſs off together.</p>
            <p>Now how ſtrangely that <hi>Turkiſh</hi> State hath been Repriev'd from Ruin, notwithſtanding the ſo many Stupendious Imperial Victories, and its Inteſtine Confuſions; and how God hath given it the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Face of a <hi>Woe</hi> again, is worthy the Conſideration of All that Bear the Name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whether <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Reform'd.</hi> And till
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105103:3"/> the <hi>Forty Two Months</hi> granted to the <hi>Beast</hi> ſhall be at an End, <hi>viz.</hi> 97. Its <hi>Conſtantinoplitan PORT</hi> ſhall not be <hi>DE-PORTED;</hi> Although this Juſt now Re-Appearance of that <hi>Mahometan</hi> Force as a <hi>Woe,</hi> and with Terror is very contrary to the declared Judgment of an <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyptic Interpreter</hi> of our own Nation, ſo Venerable, and ſo Learned, that I defer every Thing to Him, but only this; That in many ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Great Points, He hath miſt the True <hi>Key</hi> of that <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing in All Great Predictions (againſt which there are Confident Prejudices, that They ſhall not come to paſs) Thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices are as ſhutting the <hi>Mouth</hi> of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> that He ſhall not be ſo much heeded, even in his General Diſcourſes, but ſtyl'd a Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, or Brainſick perſon; As God told <hi>Ezekiel</hi> when he was to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which the <hi>Jews</hi> thought impoſible, They ſhould lay Bands upon Him as on a Mad-Man:<note place="margin">c. 3.25. c. 33.22.</note> And this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally continues, till the Great Event Fullfill'd, as it alſo Befell <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> till the <hi>City</hi> Taken, as in <hi>Symbol:</hi> So poſſibly I muſt wait for that Great <hi>Opening my Mouth</hi> with Authority, untill 97, or near it, if God ſhould pleaſe ſo Long to ſuſtain me.</p>
            <p>But yet as <hi>Ezekiel Propheſied</hi> at God's <hi>Opening his Mouth,</hi> even all along as we find, till the <hi>City</hi> taken; And he that <hi>would,</hi> might <hi>Hear,</hi> and He that <hi>would Forbear,</hi> might, untill then, <hi>Forbear.</hi> So upon God's thus far <hi>Opening my Mouth,</hi> by Ratifying my Predictions with ſo very notable Events; I look upon it as my duty to preſent to the <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> and <hi>Councel of the Nation</hi> theſe Aſſurances beyond what I have aſſured upon the ſame Grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Aſpiring of any of the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> of this Formerly <hi>Weſtern-Roman-Empire,</hi> to an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> contrary to that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of <hi>Supreme Kingdoms,</hi> God hath fixed in It, under the <hi>Emblem</hi> of <hi>Ten Toes</hi> in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's Image,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2. c. 7. Rev. 13.1.</note> and <hi>Ten Horns</hi> on the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Fourth Beast,</hi> viz. The <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> in his Viſion of the <hi>Four Beaſts,</hi> (and which the Apoſtle <hi>John ſaw Crowned;</hi>) This <hi>Tenfold</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is ſo ſettled by God, that It cannot be changed, until, As They in <hi>Ten</hi> ſuch <hi>Supremacies</hi> have <hi>Given their Power,</hi> and their <hi>Kingdom to the Papal Beast</hi> as a <hi>Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarch,</hi> that is, an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarch</hi> in an <hi>Image,</hi> as the <hi>Prophecy</hi> expreſſes it; So in the ſame <hi>Ten Kingdoms,</hi> as ſome have already, They All ſhall <hi>Hate the Whore,</hi> or <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and ſo Recall their Power from the <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As therefore the <hi>Houſe of Auſtria</hi> Aſpir'd, and Fell Low in Power, and Reputation in this Thirſt after an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy;</hi> Even ſo ſhall <hi>France;</hi> And as the diſſipation of the <hi>Spaniſh Armada</hi> againſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> was one very Remarkable Turn of the Scale, with Relation to the <hi>Houſe of Auſtria,</hi> even ſo ſhall the <hi>French</hi> Attempts againſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> be Remark'd.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105103:4"/>2. The <hi>French Proteſtant Churches</hi> cannot be long without ſome Redreſs, becauſe the Time of the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtaſie</hi> is now ſo near its end: From whence, and not from the <hi>Three Years</hi> and half of the <hi>Witneſſes lying dead,</hi> I collect this Aſſurance; For I always look'd upon that as a miſtaken Interpretation, however eſpous'd by the Two ſo Learned and Reverend Perſons Monſieur <hi>Jurieu,</hi> and the Foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd Interpreter of our own Country.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 2.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>But I look upon the Church of <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> as the <hi>Emblem</hi> of thoſe <hi>Churches of the Proteſtation,</hi> that lye in the <hi>Bowels of Princes</hi> who yet own <hi>Antichriſtian Rome;</hi> of which there is none ſo eminent, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, as the <hi>French Proteſtant Churches,</hi> either for the Greatneſs of their Body, or for their Former Vindications of Themſelves, or for their Great Sufferings, with whom the <hi>Vaudois</hi> are Allyed; Now it is ſaid, Their <hi>Last Works ſhall be Greater then their Firſt,</hi> and as their Sufferings, ſo ſhall Their Vindication be; and They ſhall ſee the Firſt Riſing of the <hi>Morning Star</hi> to the <hi>Day</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in Succeſſion, from whence I conclude; Their Deliverance is very near, and They ſhall Break their <hi>Papal</hi> Oppreſſors, as with a <hi>Rod of Iron</hi> in their <hi>Last Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Seeing there is an Extraordinary Concurrence of Gracious <hi>Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natures</hi> of God upon our preſent Soveraign, There is Great Hope God will ſtir Him up to Appear at this Time in ſo Honourable a Service, as Scripture ſtyles it, as of <hi>Helping the Lord</hi> againſt Thoſe <hi>Mighties;</hi> And if God be pleas'd to ſtir Him up, He will undoubted<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Appear with Him; For I am <hi>Bold in our God</hi> to ſay, I ſhall not be miſtaken in our King, as to ſome Extraordinary Service God hath to do by Him, the Time being ſo near; although Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> of a moſt <hi>Honourable Memory</hi> for his <hi>Apocalyptic Key,</hi> was in that ever <hi>Noble Guſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Adolphus,</hi> the time being then ſo much further off; and that on theſe Great Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That He is the <hi>Third</hi> Deſcendent of that Great <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> by whom God was pleas'd in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> to propagate the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy,</hi> and to give that Curbe to the graſp of that Time after the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy;</hi> And becauſe He Fell a <hi>Martyr</hi> in it, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd no Recompence from the Bounty of God, Equal, after the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Eſtimate of Providence,</hi> to that Service, I doubt not God hath Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd it for his Poſterity, and for the Prince that He hath Rais'd at this Time to be ſo Serviceable to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and Inſpir'd with ſo much Zeal and Courage for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our King, as Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> but now under Greater ſtyles, is One of the Princes, and Nobles of <hi>France,</hi> that as the <hi>First Works</hi> of thoſe Churches were principally by Princes, and Nobles <hi>proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Themſelves;</hi> In the ſame manner ſhall their <hi>Laſt Greater Works</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105103:4"/> be done; In which Regard, our King Appears an Inſtrument fitted by God, as a Prince and Noble <hi>proceeding</hi> from <hi>Themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God made <hi>England</hi> a Help, and a Succour by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to thoſe <hi>Afflicted Churches,</hi> though ſtill the Greateſt Effects were from <hi>Themſelves;</hi> ſo It is to be both Hoped, and Prayed, that as their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugees</hi> have by a Superior Providence working for them, Found even in the Former Reign, however of contrary Sentiments, Sanctuary here; So much more Vigorous, and Potent ſhall their Aſſiſtances be, under not only a <hi>Proteſtant Prince,</hi> but of ſo Eminent Love to, and Zeal for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> As Already there are Great Evidences of the Love, Zeal, and Forwardneſs of the <hi>Supreme Councel</hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their Unanimity herein; and Greateſt Effects are Hop'd and Pray'd for from thence.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That very <hi>Oracle,</hi> The <hi>Last Works of the Church of Thyatyra</hi> ſhall be Greater then the <hi>First,</hi> is to me an Account, why the <hi>Confederate Armies</hi> have had ſo low effects of their <hi>Confederacy,</hi> Becauſe their Princes and Nobles, of whom our King is one, ſhall <hi>proceed of Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Above All I perſevere, that within the Six next Summers, <hi>viz.</hi> in 97. The <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> ſhall be in its Succeſſion, the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> and <hi>Turkiſh Tyranny</hi> ſhall Fall, and a Great <hi>Re-Reformation</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue. And now it Theſe Things ſhall ſeem of value to ſo Soveraign an Authority, and to be every way Revered moſt Honourable an Aſſembly; Let it pleaſe them to take Care, that Conſideration may be had, whether upon Juſt Grounds, what is, or hath been offer'd, can be Refus'd, <hi>viz.</hi> on due Debates according to <hi>Records of Scripture, Chronology, Hiſtory, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Experience,</hi> without any other Reflexions, then what enter into the <hi>Merits of the Cauſe;</hi> For I <hi>Take to Witneſs</hi> the <hi>Searcher of Hearts;</hi> that as what I have now written, is not in Flattery or Diſſimulation; ſo what I have formerly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, with Relation to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> hath not been from any undervalue of the Perſonal Holineſs, and Learning of any of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency or Loweſt Name therein, for whom I have all poſſible Love and Honour; but on both ſides from moſt Aſſured Grounds in <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> That God will in an Extraordinary manner be preſent with the King, if He calls Him to Greater Services for His own Approaching <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as It is moſt Earneſtly to be pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d He may, His Honour and His Safety being therein Complicated; and that thoſe in High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Stations in the <hi>Church of England</hi> may know; The State of it, and their preſent manner of State in it hath but few Years more of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that the Great <hi>Senate</hi> of this Nation may by underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Times,</hi> and the <hi>Signs of Them, know what They ought to do,</hi> a Revolution ſo Great, indeed being ſo near as 97.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105103:5"/>
            <p>My moſt Humble Petition therefore is, That if to the moſt <hi>Dread Soveraigns,</hi> and to the <hi>High Court of Parliament,</hi> It ſhall not be made to Appear; That what hath been publickly offer'd as a <hi>Table of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Prophecy,</hi> and its <hi>Calendar of Time,</hi> is upon Foundations, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inconſiſtent with Themſelves, or Contradictory to <hi>Scripture, Chronology, Hiſtory</hi> or <hi>Reaſon;</hi> There may be an Eye Had in all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations, and Actions thereunto, as to the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Spirit of Prophecy;</hi> Seeing It is moſt Agreeable to all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Reaſon, God ſhould give to ſo Illuſtrious a Soveraign Power, Senate, and to ſo Great Proteſtant Nations, ſome ſigns of ſo Great, and ſo near an Approaching Time; And that Your moſt Self Abaſed Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt in theſe <hi>Propheſies</hi> may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and enabled to Reviſe, Perfect, and Publiſh his whole Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and preſent it together to ſo <hi>Supreme Powers,</hi> as a Volumn that will within Six next enſuing Summers, Juſtifie it ſelf, and further our Accounts at the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and Appearing of our Infinitely Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount <hi>Lord Jeſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if This Petition Receive Favour, let alſo the Councel of ſo Humble a Miniſter of, and according to the <hi>Propheſies</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> be Accepted to ſo Great Eſtates; In which, I Appeal to God, I moſt Humbly and Earneſtly pray, I may ſpeak as, and only as the <hi>Oracles of God</hi> in theſe Four Moments of Advice from <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Advice</hi> 1. That the <hi>Arms</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Refugees</hi> of <hi>France</hi> of the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> of Proteſtants in general, be more valued, and under God more Relyed upon, then mixed <hi>Confederacies,</hi> with <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and States, that yet <hi>Give their Power</hi> to the <hi>Roman Beast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give leave therefore to Weigh in the Ballance of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> each part; Firſt, ſhewing the diſadvantages to be Feared in mixed <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracies,</hi> in Two Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ought to be well pondered, that at this very Time, All <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> who yet <hi>Give their Kingdom</hi> to the <hi>Beast,</hi> are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as yet in a <hi>State of War</hi> with the <hi>Lamb,</hi> that is with <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> now about to Reprize wholly, and perfectly his <hi>Kingdom</hi> from that <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the Main Cauſe of Diſpute at this Time betwixt this Nation and <hi>France,</hi> is a <hi>Proteſtant Government,</hi> and indeed the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in general in the World; Whether the <hi>Lamb</hi> will Accept the Service of Them, who are in <hi>Actual War,</hi> is much to be doubted; eſpecially, when He hath been, and is ſtill giving ſuch mighty Demonſtrations of his Preſence with us, and of his <hi>Arm made Bare</hi> in this very Proteſtant Cauſe; It may be very dangerous to over-value the <hi>Arm of Fleſh</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Confederacy.</hi> In this Caſe we
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105103:5"/> ſhould be as much Aſhamed, as <hi>Ezra</hi> of <hi>Perſian Aſſiſtances;</hi> Seeing that the <hi>Hand of our God is for Good on all Them that ſeek Him,</hi> and His <hi>Wrath</hi> is againſt <hi>All Them that Forſake Him</hi> at this Time, as to the great Cauſe of <hi>Proteſtancy;</hi> For this God hath now <hi>written</hi> in this <hi>Nation</hi> with a <hi>Sun Beam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Succeſs that hath hitherto Attended this <hi>Confederacy,</hi> is not ſuch as to give any Hopes, God will manifeſt Himſelf with it; He hath ſuffer'd all the Motions of it to be Clogg'd, and Heavy, to prove Ineffectual, and on the Looſing Hand; as it were to declare, The <hi>Principals</hi> in it, are not yet Inſtruments fitted for his Service in the Proſecution of that Intereſt, He is now purſuing in the World, and ſo particularly in theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We know, the moſt <hi>Native Adminiſtration</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> in the Grand <hi>Confederates,</hi> is Perſecution of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition upon it: What Wonder then, if ſuch Blended Intereſts are un-ſucceſsful? And it is now the more conſiderable, that the Wheels of Providence, where Things are Right ſet, will be, as we have ſeen, with a <hi>Divine ſpeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I do Freely Acknowledge, There are Two Things that ſeem to Counterſway, and Incline to the <hi>Confederacy</hi> on the other ſide.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as it hath been ſaid, the State of the <hi>Weſtern Chriſtendom,</hi> (as It may be call'd; but is indeed in the Greater parts of it <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom</hi>) is by <hi>Prophecy</hi> determined into Ten, or a Multiplicity of <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> On this Account, Any of the Ten, though if not Revuls'd from the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> they are in <hi>Prophetic Language, Horns</hi> of the <hi>Papacy,</hi> may yet be us'd by God, as heretofore, to hold that Multiplicity Equal and Firm; and ſo may ſerve to Reduce any one, that would ſwell beyond its due Scituation, and Proportion of Room on that <hi>Head:</hi> And this is indeed the Higheſt Amount of what hath been, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Hardly hath been done by the <hi>Confederacy</hi> as yet; God having ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd for great Reaſons, as will ere long Appear, ſo dangerous an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travaſation</hi> of the <hi>French Power,</hi> even as if It were the <hi>Beaſtian Power,</hi> and in its 666. as ſome Learned Men have Thought among us, but will ſoon ſo Retrench it, as to ſhew that opinion to be meer miſtake, and I am aſſur'd eſpecially by Thoſe, I have Juſt now declar'd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How far the <hi>Confederacy</hi> of Proteſtants with <hi>Papal Powers,</hi> may be of uſe to Encline them to the <hi>Reformation,</hi> God having made uſe of outward Force not ſo much, in Enclining Princes to Fall off from <hi>Rome</hi> in the <hi>Beginning Reformation,</hi> as of more <hi>Evangelical</hi> Methods, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and Free Communications of Truth, Providential, and Friendly Obligations, much more now; But I fear the Time of the great <hi>Re-Reformation,</hi> though ſo near, is not near enough at this Time to hope yet for ſo Bleſſed a Fruit of the <hi>Confederacy,</hi> nor does any Thing Appear like it.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105103:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Adv.</hi> 2. I would moſt Humbly Adviſe, that there might be under ſo Great an Authority, and Influence, an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of Men, Learned and Loving the <hi>Kingdom of our Lard Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who might diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo Admirable a part, (Hitherto it may be call'd a <hi>Terra Incognita</hi>) of Scripture, even the Stupendious <hi>Propheſies</hi> of it; Firſt, by Single, and then Compared and Joyned endeavours; For They now are big, and ready to Travel in their Completion; The Ignorance of which, is a greater Reproach of <hi>Theologers,</hi> then ſome Diſeaſes of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> and is a Judiciary Blindneſs on all Chriſtians during the <hi>Apoſtaſie:</hi> The Affairs of Nations are more concern'd therein, then in Forming Armies, and Equipping Navys, which are but Subordinate to thoſe Completions, and often not ſo much as that, as we have ſeen.</p>
            <p>I am bold to ſay, if I had, as now God hath vouchſafed me, underſtood <hi>Prophecy</hi> in the Years 48, 50, and ſo onward in the very Top of Thoſe Powers over the <hi>Nation,</hi> and kept cloſe and ſteddy to the Guidance of it; I ſhould certainly have Foreſeen the Re-enſtating the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that lay then in the Duſt, and ſo of the <hi>Royal Family</hi> that ſhould do it.</p>
            <p>And as according to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> even in the Full Tyde of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Victories, I declar'd the Impoſſibility of the <hi>Turks,</hi> being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted from the <hi>Conſtantinoplitan Heighths;</hi> Even ſo, and much more might by ſuch Compared Reſearches, the Affairs of Nations, and Churches be ſo underſtood, as to be Conducted with greater Judgment, and Reſolution; And what could ſo great a Proteſtant <hi>Aſſembly</hi> take with more Sageneſs and Honour under their Care and <hi>Patronage,</hi> of more Honour then <hi>Ptolemy</hi>'s 70?</p>
            <p>Particularly the State of the preſent Government in the Aſſurance of its Stability reſts on the Reſolution of one Illuſtrious Point of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, viz.</hi> The <hi>Slaying of the Witneſſes,</hi> whether It be paſt or not; For if it were not, ſeeing the True Senſe of it is a Suppreſſion of All <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches</hi> for a Time, It is not I, but the Thing it ſelf ſpeaks, This <hi>Revolution</hi> muſt of neceſſity Revolve.</p>
            <p>For as in Reſcue of theſe Nations from the Return of <hi>Popery,</hi> This <hi>Revolution</hi> came, even miraculouſly to paſs, much more by the Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> then by Humane <hi>Sageſſe</hi> or Power; So if ſuch a <hi>Slaying of the Witneſſes</hi> were ye to be; There would certainly to ſerve Providence therein, be a Return of <hi>Romiſh Power,</hi> which muſt of neceſſity Roll back this <hi>Revolution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But although the mention of the <hi>Three days,</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> as the moſt Immediate Precedent of their <hi>Riſing,</hi> and its Great Concomitants ſeem to Favour ſuch an Apprehenſion, Although the Senſe of many excellent Perſons, and very underſtanding in <hi>Prophecy,</hi> particularly if Truly His, that <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>A. B.</hi> Uſher, encline that way and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105103:6"/> Laſtly, Although the uſual manner of God Introducing his great <hi>Deliverances</hi> by very dark Prefaces, would much perſwade it; Yet as I am moſt Aſſured, the main Senſe (as I have already publiſhed) of the <hi>Three Days and a Half,</hi> Intends a much Longer Time, even the whole <hi>Deep Time</hi> of the <hi>Antichriſtian Reign,</hi> parallel to the <hi>Lying of Christ in the Grave;</hi> ſo there are great Conſiderations that aſſure me, There cannot be ſo much as an <hi>Epitome,</hi> or Compendious <hi>Slaying of the Witneſſes,</hi> or ſo dark a State upon <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> yet to come.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Time of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> Full and Total Riſing, is ſo near, that there cannot poſſibly be Time for the Operation of the Inſtruments of their ſuppreſſion, or <hi>Slaying,</hi> of <hi>their Lying Dead,</hi> and then for their <hi>Riſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe there is a State of <hi>Proteſtant Churches,</hi> that are ſo ſecur'd, as by a Divine Determination; That They cannot from their Firſt Settlement in the <hi>Reformation</hi> be any more Reduced under <hi>Popiſh Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very;</hi> of which ſort, one of the Principal is the <hi>Church of England;</hi> as Appear'd by the ſudden Jealouſie, that awoke at thoſe Eſſays of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery to Re-Invade it; and the univerſal Zeal of the Nation to Stemm that Tyde that was offering to Flow in, was a moſt undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Impreſſion from Heaven, upon ſo many that have too little Senſe of the Power of that profeſſion upon Them to be otherwiſe mov'd.</p>
            <p>And if It ſhould ſeem to be any Objection, that the <hi>Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> lay ſo long ſuppreſs'd as from 42, to 60. I have no deſire to ſay it, but Truth obliges me to ſay, that even that Judgment upon it was for its ſo Voluntary Returns to more in the <hi>Synagogue of Sathan,</hi> under the pretence of Antiquity, then could be Allowed by its very own Standard of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and as a Sample of the perfect Removal of that its very <hi>Standard</hi> (as not Seal'd in the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> nor of <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Juſt <hi>Temple-Weights, Meaſures,</hi>) and ſo to be by the great <hi>Re-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> Broken.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe Suffering <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> have but Time before the <hi>Full Riſing</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> to do their Laſt <hi>Greater Works</hi> then their Firſt, and to ſee the <hi>Dawns</hi> of the <hi>Morning Star</hi> in their Vindication from, and Victory over their <hi>Oppreſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adv.</hi> 3. Let it pleaſe ſo great Princes, and Councels, to ſet before Them the Late <hi>Doings of God</hi> by the <hi>Turkiſh,</hi> again prevailing Force, and judge whether It does not, as in a Mirrour, ſhew ſuch a Length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of that <hi>Woe</hi> on the ſo called <hi>Chriſtian World,</hi> while the <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Worſhip</hi> of <hi>Wood</hi> and <hi>Stone,</hi> the <hi>Thefts,</hi> the <hi>Sorceries,</hi> and <hi>Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the Romiſh Communion</hi> ſtill continue; And that this very Thing might be, and hath been predicted according to <hi>Prophecy;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of how great Moment, Judgment according to <hi>Prophecy</hi> is, even beyond Victory it ſelf, It being predicted in the midſt of <hi>Imperial Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105103:7"/>
            <p>And therefore the <hi>whole Council</hi> of God, as to the <hi>Powers</hi> of theſe Nations cannot be declar'd by Preaching, without Reſearch of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> eſpecially Concerning the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual regard had to it, Let the <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Rethorick</hi> of Such diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes be otherwiſe never ſo Great.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adv.</hi> 4. Let it pleaſe the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Queen,</hi> and the <hi>Nobles,</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> Aſſembled; that the moſt Powerful <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>-way of Preaching and Prayer, may have All Advantages of Encouragement given, to ſpread abroad in Cities, Towns, and Countreys; and moſt Eminently in <hi>Camps</hi> and <hi>Navies,</hi> that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Debauchery, Prophaneſs, and Atheiſticneſs, that is ſo Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly abroad, may be quench'd; And that Choice of Perſons, who are to Adventure their Lives, may be made ſo far, as is poſſible, of ſuch, who have a Knowledge of that Excellent Cauſe, <hi>Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> for which They ſo adventure: For though with very Un-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Proteſtants, as once He ſaid with <hi>Wounded Men,</hi> God hath and will ſtill work for his Names ſake for a while; Yet nearer the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> He will not endure ſuch Perſons; Let us therefore <hi>prepare a High way for our God,</hi> and make <hi>His Paths ſtreight:</hi> And They who thus Honour God, He will honour, but They who deſpiſe him, ſhall <hi>be Lightly eſteemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us not therefore (to Conclude) Hope their Hope, not Fear their Fear, who meaſure All ſafety, and Succeſs by a <hi>Confederacy,</hi> tho' mixed on one ſide, and Slaviſhly Fear a <hi>Papal Confederacy</hi> on the other; But let us Sanctifie the Lord of Hoſts Himſelf, with an Emphaſis, as we are commanded, and let <hi>Him be our Fear and our Dread. Iſa.</hi> 8.13.</p>
            <p>Let us know, God Alarms the King, and theſe Nations, to ſerve Him in <hi>France;</hi> And it is to he hop'd and pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d rather then that we ſhould not, He will neceſſitate us; For if we do not, it is moſt certain, the Government will Fall into Diſhonour firſt, and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Confuſion, Laſtly, into Ruin.</p>
            <p>Now if Theſe Things be deſpiſed, diſbelieved or Ridicul'd, It is but what Reception <hi>Prophecy,</hi> however Adminiſtred hath always Found in the World; But it cannot be <hi>Judged by Mans day,</hi> I <hi>count therefore nothing dear</hi> to Fulfill this <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> and I ſhall always Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in its Acceptance, ſo as may abound to the Account of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepters; Eſpecialiy in Yours, to me Moſt <hi>Awful Supreme Powers;</hi> For whom I dayly bow my Knees, as a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt to ſo great <hi>Principalities, Miniſtring</hi> to you the <hi>Divine Propheſies;</hi> and that Your (not to ſay, mine) <hi>Offering up Your ſelves</hi> according to them, may be a <hi>Sacrifice Acceptable to God,</hi> being <hi>Sanctified by the Holy Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105103:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
